A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Hospital, General Files, Series 1 FA228
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Hospital, General Files, Series 1
1910-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Cole, Rufus
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA228
6.84 Cubic Feet 11 boxes and 2 packages.
11 boxes and 2 packages.
Other Finding Aids
FA837 Rockefeller University records, Hospital, Administrative Correspondence, Series 2.
FA838 Rockefeller University records, Hospital, Subject Files, Series 3.
FA909 Rockefeller University records, Hospital, Collected Reprints, Series 4.
Arrangement
The Rockefeller University records, Hospital is arranged in four series:
Series 1: General Files. Series 2: Administrative Correspondence. Series 3: Subject Files. Series 4: Collected Reprints.
Series 3 is closed to scholarly research pending further processing.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment. Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 430
Conditions Governing Access note
This material is open for scholarly research.
Operations management; Medical care; Medical education; Medical research; Medical technology; Medical sciences; Medicine, Preventive; Hospitals; Rockefeller University; Cole, Rufus; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Historical items
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  On the closing of one of the hospital wards in January 1977, Miss Armstrong turned over to the archives several items of historical interest from the closed ward (in box 2).
  - Receipts and disbursements, 1908 September-1910 December 23; carbon copy (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Equipment lists with prices, 1910; 2 volumes, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Hospital equipment: authorized, ordered, received.
  - Photographs; nursing staff, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes group photos, individual portraits of Miss Alice N. Lockie, 1938; Miss Georgina M. Drew, 1938; Miss Stella R. Hoffmann, 1938.
  - Photograph of ambulance, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photograph album: "The Rockefeller Institute Hospital, 1910-1955", 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Prepared for 1977 commencement when honorary degrees were conferred upon Alan Rushton Battersby, Michael Heidelberger, and Irvine Heinly Page. Consists of hospital staff photographs.
  - Photograph album, "The Rockefeller Hospital", 1910-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Staff photographs, 1910-1981. The Rockefeller Hospital, 1982.
  - 2 volumes, 1986 October 22 (Box 1)
    [2 volumes previously in Box 1 moved to Box 9, ck, 22 Oct 86.].
  - Oxygen chamber (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Stadie, W.C. "The development of controlled oxygen therapy". Address delivers May 19, Chicago on presentation of Willard Gibbs medal to D.D. Van Slyke (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photograph of oxygen chamber (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Report of fire in the oxygen chamber (November 17, 1922) which includes signed statements from nurse, night superintendent, etc. Patient Anna Couche died. (carbon copy) Another copy in RG417 with some pictures after the fire, 1922 November 17; 16 pp. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Instructions: Stacking Oxygen Chamber, 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Binger, Carl A.L. "The construction and management of an oxygen chamber" Reprint from The Modern Hospital 24 (1925) 186-194 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Signs, 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Warning.
    Directions for charging and operating oxygen chamber.
    Precautions essential to safe operation of the oxygen chamber.
  - Waller, Dorothy S. "Nutritive value of foods" (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Eli Lilly slide rule for computing diets.
  - Operating directions for sterilizers, 3 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Release dated 1915 October 27 signed by Edw. Denninger for taking of blood and countersigned by Harold L. Amoss (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Also signed receipt dated Oct. 23, 1915 for payment of $20.00 and release for the Hospital of all responsibility.
  - News and Notes: articles on clinical research in The Rockefeller University Hospital: I, II, and clinical science (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - v. 8, no. 1, 1976 October
    - v. 8, no. 5, 1975 November
    - v. 9, no. 4, 1978 January
  - The Johns Hopkins Medical Journal v. 143 no. 3, 1978 September (Box 2, Folder 6)
    pp. 84-103 article by A. McGehee Harvey. G. Canby Robinson: Peripatetic Medical Educator (he was the first resident in the newly opened Hospital of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research and this article has a section on the early days of the hospital.).
  - Petty cash journal, 1910 October 26-1916 November 2; 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Payroll book, 1910 September 15-1917 June 30; 1 volume (Box 2)
  - 9 black notebooks labeled DIET KITCHEN, DOCTORS" ORDER BOOK (Box 2)
  - Signed orders for various food formulae, September 1954-October 1955; October 1955-November 1956; November 1956-January 1958; January 1958-November 1958; 1958 November-November 1959; 1959 November-May 1961; 1961 May-October 1962; 1962 October-July 1963; 1963 July-June 1964 (Box 2)
- Historical records, 1910-1959; 4 boxes 1 package (21 inches)
  Biographical/Historical note
  In 1977 Kathy Kleinbard became Administrator of the Hospital and sent to the archives a group of materials which were records that were kept by the hospital for many years.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged by subject.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Received or inventoried: 1978
  - Appreciation letters, 1938-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Sent to various hospital personnel 1938-1967 Chronologically arranged. Includes letters from Marcia Davenport quoted in G.W. Corner History of the Institute.
  - untitled (Box 3, Folder 1A)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Closed.
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - American Hospital Association (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Samuel G. Braun (Prosperity Co.) laundry system (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Construction, 1946-1952 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Floor plans, Correspondence, minutes of meetings between Institute representatives and Coolidge, Shepley, Bull-finch and Abbott and Vermilya-Brown dealing with the building of the hospital addition.
  - Construction (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Drawings and specifications for hospital addition (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Furnishings, 1949-1952 October (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Estimates and expenditures (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Procedures for employees, 1935-1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - Regulations for nurses and dietitians, undated
    - Covering letter with 1935 procedures outlined by, 1937
    - Counsel regarding furnishing of patients' records
    - Pharmacy use regulations, 1939
    - Posting of orders and medication dispensing, 1949
    - Operation permission slips, 1950
    - Regulations for isolation, 1951
    - Precautions regarding isolation chamber, undated
    - Instructions concerning patients' histories, 1951
    - Memorandum on isolation, 1952
    - Visiting hours, 1952 1955 1958
    - Procedures needing reemphasis, 1959
    - Compliance with Federal Narcotics regulations, 1959
  - Procedures of physicians affiliated with the Hospital, 1957-1960 1962 1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Signed entries of nurses time and hours, 4 bound volumes (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1949-1953
    - 1953-1956
    - 1956-1959
    - 1971-1974
  - Time book for orderlies and aides, 1969-1973; 1 bound volume (Box 4)
  - Hospital budgets, 50 pamphlets (duplicated copies) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1911/1912-1959/1960
    - 1968/1969
      1968/1969 budget and correspondence about salary increases 1970 Jan. 29 Magie to Drew re. salary increases.
    - Budget, 1970/1971
    - Tabulation: History and wage schedules of hospital employees, 1938
  - Navy statistics, 1942-1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Hospital admissions and transfers. Shows service on which patient is admitted but does not necessarily indicate condition. Includes patient days, by month, Navy census by hospital service.
  - Hospital admissions and discharges, 1910 October-1919 July; 4 bound volumes (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1919-1927
    - 1927-1931
    - 1931-1934
    - 1935-1942
  - Continues Register of patients, 4 bound volumes (Box 6)
    - 1942 May-1953 May
    - 1953 May-1957 October
    - 1957 October-1961 October
    - 1961 October-1965 December
  - 2 certificates from Joint Commission on Accreditation of Hospitals, 1955 1958; package (Box 6)
  - 1 Patient chart - enlarged; includes colored markings (Box 6)
- Superintendent of Hospital, 1938-1967; 1 box 2 1/2 inches
  - Journal, reports, receipts, and other material
    - Journal, 4 bound volumes (Box 7)
      Labeled vol. 1, 2, 3, 4. Records of petty cash disbursements.
      - 1936-1945
      - 1945-1957
      - 1957-1966
      - 1967-1974
    - Record of patients money vol. 5, 1937-1949; 1 small bound volume (Box 7)
      Deposited in safe and withdrawn.
    - Receipt book of patients vol. 6 property, 1948-1949; 1 small bound volume (Box 7)
    - Record of Morticians, vol. 7, 4/29/1938-December 1967 (Box 7)
      Cites name of patient; date of death; name of undertaker, address, tel. no., date, time, permit no. of removal of body, signature of mortician.
      Examples of names found: Alma Zimbalist, Dr. Charles Stockard Alfred Smith; Dr. Homer Swift; Charles L. Hoagland.
    - Stapled sheets "Registry of Deaths", vol. 8, 1961 November-1967 December (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1956-
    Date received or inventoried: 1980
    - Civil Defense, 1951-1956 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Consists of arrangements for evacuation and care in the event of an emergency. Includes a route plan with New York Hospital.
    - Correspondence scattered, 1956-1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Correspondence with Superintendent of Hospital; Director of nurses, Dr. Horsfall, Paul Penndorf, Waldo Flinn and Dr. M. McCarty on matters of administration.
    - Rufus Cole Lecture. Announcement of lecture by Dr. Eugene Braunwald, "Protection of the Ischemic Myocardium", 1978 February 27 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Rufus Cole Lecture, reprint of article based on the Rufus Cole lecture by Alexander G. Bearn, M.D. "The Pharmaceutical Industry and Academe: Partners in Progress" The American Journal of Medicine, Volume 71 (July 1981) 81-88, 1980 June 4 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Booklet, with enclosures, "The Rockefeller University Hospital: Environment for Discovery", 1981; 12 pp., 2 copies (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Enclosures are 1-page each descriptions of laboratories: "Endocrinology" "Human Behavior and Metabolism" "Cutaneous Biology and Investigative Dermatology" "Metabolism-Pharmacology" "Bacteriology and Immunology" "Medical Biochemistry" "Lipid and Lipoprotein Metabolism"
      Received 9 November 1982 (E. Straight).
  - Registry of Death forms, Stapled booklets (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1939 May-September
    - 1939 December-1940 April
    - 1940 April-August
    - 1941 January-March
    - 1941 November-1942 March
  - Death certifications. Board of Health, New York City, circa 1936-1938 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Narcotic regulations. Correspondence and printed matter, 1938 1952 1963 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    (See also Bernard Lupinek biographical file).
- Electric ambulance, circa 1911; 4 items (Box 8, Folder 8)
  Includes clipping, undated, from The Edison Monthly with photo of RIMR Hospital ambulance.
  Received 1 October 1984 from Carmen Schmidt via Sonya W. Mirsky with folder labeled "Mr. Lupinek".
- Frank E. Chapman, Hospital Organization and Operation (New York, The Macmillan Co., 1924). The Modern Hospital Library (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Joseph J. Weber, First Steps in Organizing A Hospital. An Exposition of Ideals and Principles Incident to the Inception and Organization of a Hospital (New York: The Macmillan Co., 1924). The Modern Hospital Library (Box 8, Folder 8)
- The Rockefeller University Hospital. A Bridge Between Science Healing, 1985 September; Illustrated booklet. 12 pp. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  Received October 1985.
- Pamphlets: "The Rockefeller University Hospital Clinical Research Center" Conditions under Study, 1985. Conditions under Study, 1986, 1985-1986; 1 copy of each (Box 8, Folder 10)
  Received January 1986 (Kathy Kleinbard).
- "The Rockefeller University Hospital Staff Directory. 1910-1985" circa January 1986 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Photocopies from Johns Hopkins Archives: Nancy P. Ellicott. Articles by/about, from Nurses Alumnae Magazine, 1903-1944; 27 pp. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  Received 1986 April 29 (Elizabeth Straight).
- Orders, authorizations, and distribution of supplies for the Hospital, circa 1910; 2 hand-written volumes, 2.5" letter. (Box 9)
  - 1 "Book 2304" [on inside front cover], circa 1910
    Includes: orders and authorizations for Furniture, Kitchen equipment, Linen, Laboratory instruments, Nursing supplies, Sterilizers, Physiological apparatus, X-ray apparatus, etc.
  - Distribution of goods ordered for Hospital" [1st page], 1910 May 2
    Indicates number of various items designated for basement, Doctors, Nurses, Wards (by number), Supply, Isolation.
- Brochure. "The Rockefeller University Hospital Clinical Research Center. Conditions under Study, 1987" The Rockefeller University Hospital, January 1987, 5 copies (Box 10, Folder 1)
  Received 27 January 1987 from Kathy Kleinbard.
- Brochure. "The Rockefeller University Hospital Clinical Research Center. Conditions Under Study, 1988" The Rockefeller University Hospital, January, 1988, 2 copies (Box 10, Folder 2)
  Received 1 Jan 1988, from Kathy Kleinbard.
- Medical Staff By-Laws and Rules & Regulations, 1977 January (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Revision - December 1980.
- "The Rockefeller University Hospital Clinical Research Center. Conditions Under Study, 1989" The Rockefeller University Hospital, January 1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- "The Rockefeller University Hospital Clinical Research Center, Conditions Under Study, 1990" The Rockefeller University Hospital, 1990 January (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Drug and Supply Notebooks, 1963-1977 (Box 11)
  Scope and Contents
  Inventory of drugs and supplies kept by nurses on Ward 3 and 4 of the clinic
- Guest book, 1913-1948; Package 2
  Among signatures are Helen of Romania, Elizabeth of Belgium.
  Date received or inventoried: 1974 January 23
  Bound volume.